[music]
Ladies and gentlemen, give it up [music]
for Marcus D. Wally. [cheering]
[music and cheering]
What's up?
All right.
[cheering]
>> What's up? How everybody doing?
>> I want to jump right into it. Ever since
I dropped my special marriage is major
surgery,
>> people think I am a marriage counselor.
[laughter]
I'm not. Just because I am verified on
social media don't mean I'm qualified to
counsel. [laughter]
Me and my wife argue all the time. Uh I
find it quite healthy. Uh the the Bible
say iron sharpens iron. It's going to be
some friction sometime. I am not a
marriage counselor. Me and my wife, we
go to bed angry sometimes. The Bible
frowns upon that. Somewhere in there it
says, "Do not let the sun go down on
your wrath."
We tried it.
I'm still mad. And no, I don't want to
pray. Okay. But when that happens, I get
on my side of the bed, she get on her
side of the bed, but our feet still
touch.
We still in love. Ain't nobody going
nowhere. But yeah, I am not a marriage
counselor, but what I am is a
relationship
expert. That's what I am, a relationship
expert. I got this title one day. I was
in the bed watching this show on TV
called Fatal Attraction.
What Fatal Attraction is, for those you
have never seen it, uh it's about a love
that's gone bad. Um typically somebody
gets possessive, somebody get jealous,
and then somebody die. And so I'm
watching it and and and those episodes
are normally narrated by the detectives
from the police department, by
psychiatrists, psychologists,
counselors, but this particular episode,
it was narrated by a relationship
expert. I looked up and I noticed the
relationship expert was a guy that go to
my church. So when I saw that, I said,
"Oh my god, I can't wait to get to
church. I'm not going for a word from
the Lord." Uh, I'm not going for praise
and worship. I'm going to see him this
Sunday. And so I got to church and when
I got to church, I went up to him. I
said, "Say cuz I saw you on Fatal
Attraction." And he was like, "Oh yeah,
you seen that?" "Oh yeah, that's how he
talk." "Oh yeah, yeah, you seen that." I
said, "Yeah, I saw you on there." I want
to know how does one become a
relationship expert? He said, "Well, you
know, uh, I went to school. I got my BA
in this, my MA in that, my PhD in this.
I said, "Yeah, yeah, I went to school,
too." Uh, but
but I'm trying to say, "How how does one
become a relationship expert?" He said,
"Well, you know, we do case studies. We
do research, statistics, all that type
of stuff." I said, "Yeah, I do the same
thing in my barber shop, case by case
with the guys, talking about their
relationships." Yeah. Yeah. But how does
one become a relationship expert? He
said, "I just told you." I said, "Well,
I'm one. [laughter]
I am now a relationship expert." Yeah.
The reason why I'm saying because this
dude here, he ain't even married. And
I'm trying to see how you're expert in
something that you not even in.
I'm an expert. See, I know how to be in
a house with a woman I love and we ain't
talk in 5 days. [laughter]
That's expert talking right there.
See, I know how we ain't talked in 5
days, but we got to go to somebody's get
together, some gathering, and we ain't
talk, but now we got to act like we've
been talking. We in there front. She in
there. Here go, baby. Here go your
plate. Oh, baby. Here go your seat. Go.
Sit down. Then we get back in the car,
drive back home. No talking. That is a
relationship expert.
Yeah. So, I am self-ordained,
self-anointed, self-appointed,
relationship, but I like to call it real
relationship expert, not relationship
because relationship experts, they try
to fix relationships.
That's not what I do. Because I know
some of you like it broke.
And I'm not mad at you. You know, do
what you do. Okay. Yeah. But so I go by
a real relationship
expert. What I do, I tell my friends the
real. I give them real perspective, real
insight, okay? Real light on the subject
matter, real opinions. Okay? Like for
instance, one of my boys in the barber
shop, cuz that's my second church. Uh
one of the guys in the barber shop, he
come to me and say, "Hey, Mark, man,
marriage ain't what I imagined it to
be." I said, "What?" He said, "Yeah, it
ain't what I imagined, bro. I imagine
she would be doing this. I imagine
she'll be doing that. I was like, "And
she ain't doing it." He said, "No, she
ain't doing it. I don't like it." I
said, "Well, you shouldn't have a
problem with marriage. You should have a
problem with your imagination."
You see how real that is right there?
Yeah. Marriage didn't let you down. Your
imagination let you down. Yeah. And I
And I know that Bible that Bible tell
you to cast down every imagination. And
for those you that don't read the Bible,
the temptations told you it was just my
imagination
running away.
I give them real just just just real
insight, real perspective. Like one of
the things I like to tell people, you
can cut down on the arguments in your
marriage if you recognize and realize
that men and women have different
listening skills.
>> Watch this. different listening skills.
Each of us have a skill, but it's
different. Ladies, men are bottom line
listeners. We're only listening
for the bottom line.
I know when you get home, you want to
tell your man about your whole
ARE YOU LISTENING? I AM, but I'm only
listening for the bottom line,
fellas. Women are detailoriented
listeners. They only listening for
details. Okay? That's why when you come
home a little later than usual and your
woman is at home, she done took a
shower. She got on cocoa butter, shea
butter, all the butters. She's smelling
good. She done prepared you something to
eat, you know. And you walk in the door,
she asks you a little question. She's
not trying to be your boss. She's not
trying to interrogate you. She's not
trying to run you, investigate. She
trying to do none of that. It's just a
little question she asked because you
came in a little later than usual. Her
little question is just, "Hey bae, where
you been,
but because you was raised by an old
fool,
somebody that told you, man, DON'T LET
NO WOMAN question you." You can't ANSWER
A LITTLE BITTY QUESTION. So you say
something like out
and to a woman out equals sin.
Out don't give no details.
So now she going through your pants and
your phone and your email cuz you just
won't give no details. [laughter]
Yeah. Men, bottom line, women detail.
Let me give it better. When my wife is
in the mall and she sees some shoes that
exceeds her budget, some shoes she don't
want to spend with her money, what
she'll do is call me and say, "Hey bae,
I see these shoes. Can you get them for
me? I have one question.
How much?" [laughter] Bottom line. Here
she go. They red. [laughter]
How much? They not open toe. They not
closed toe. THEY PEEPED TOE. SAYING,
"HOW MUCH?"
When men and women go on dates, women
when they tell their lady friends, they
girlfriends about the date is full of
details. It's one of the worst
conversations. [laughter]
One of the worst back and forths you
will ever hear. When a woman go out with
a man and she talking to her girls about
the day, it be something like this.
Girl, you ain't going to believe this.
Listen to me. He asked me out. He sent a
car to come pick me up. Yes, a car came
to my house. Pick me up. When I got in
the car, he had written a handwritten
letter talking about when he first saw
me, he knew he wanted to get with me,
but he wanted to get his stuff together.
So, he didn't approach me then. And then
I get to the restaurant. It's a
five-star restaurant. We have a five
course meal. They just kept bringing
food and bringing food. I ain't never
ate so much before. At the table,
balloons and flowers and all type of
little candies and girl. And we talked
and he looked me in my eyes when he
talked to me and we had a wonderful
conversation. And when we left the
restaurant, he drove us to a lake. We
went and walked around the lake and we
talked all night. Girl, he was smelling
so good. He had this cologne on. Oh, he
had me at that cologne. And so we talked
and then he took me home, walked me to
the door. I'm not going to lie, I wanted
him to come in. I did. But he said he
want tonight to remain pure. And so he
kissed me on the forehead. I told him to
call me when he got home. And guess
what, girl? HE CALLED [screaming]
and we talked till the sun came up. And
all her girls be there like,
>> "I THINK HE THE [screaming] ONE."
[laughter]
NOW, the man that was on that same date,
when he tell his partners about that
same date, this how it go for him. He go
right in there. Hey, y'all know I went
out with old girl last night. HIS
PARTNERS GOT ONE QUESTION.
>> Did you hear? You already know.
[applause and cheering] D YOUR HEAD
BOTTOM LINE [laughter]
BECAUSE WE DON'T WANT TO KNOW ABOUT THE
DETAILS UNTIL WE HIT THE BOTTOM LINE.
But because women are detailoriented
listeners, I believe women make better
friends.
That's not Bible. That's my opinion that
women make better friends. Reason they
make better friends is because of the
details. Like let's say if a if a man
was to walk into like a Chili's
restaurant, he walks into Chili's and
and he see his best friend, his homeboy
lady in there with another man. When a
man walk in and see that man, we hurt.
You hear me? We walk in, we
Reason [laughter]
[laughter]
why we hurt is because we know how much
our dude love this girl and it's going
to crush him. So some men won't even
tell their partner because we don't want
to be the one to hurt him. Now the men
that will tell their partner, they tell
him but they don't give him no details.
So when they call him, it be like this
here.
What up, boy?
You still with Kim?
Don't look like it.
I don't know who he is. She in here with
him. No. Handle your business. I'll holl
at you. Nothing.
Now when she come home, he got nothing
to fight with. HE JUST ANGRY. WHERE YOU
BEEN? OUT WITH WHO? THE GIRLS. WHERE YOU
WAS AT? JELLIES. I HEARD YOU WAS WITH A
DUDE. IT WAS A BUNCH OF DUDES IN THERE.
Calm down. Breathe.
[laughter]
He just mad. But reverse it. Let's say a
woman walks in the chilies and she see
her best friend, her girl man in there
with another woman. First of all, when
she walk in, she ain't sad. This how she
walk in. I knew it. [laughter]
I knew it. I KNEW IT. [screaming] I KNEW
IT. TRIED TO TELL HER HE AIN'T UH-HUH.
Trying to tell her she all in love. So
stupid. Dumb in love.
Why she not hurt?
If she didn't graduate from high school,
she going over there.
Sir, who is this? No. Who? Ma'am, don't
get slapped. Who is this?
But let's say she graduated from high
school
when she called this how she called her
girl. Hey girl,
>> what Eric said he was at
work. [clears throat]
He work at chilies
[laughter] now cuz he in here he got a
oldtime with cheese girl with got a
three for me. She a little lightkinned
girl raggedy split ends mole on the
right side of her face. drive a green
Malibu. Luck has been shot up on the
right hand side, work at the hospital on
the third floor. SHE'S A PHABOTAMIST AND
WENT TO HIGH SCHOOL WITH US.
[laughter]
So now when Eric come home, she got the
whole rap sheet. He walk in the door.
Hey babe, she where you been? He work.
You work at chilies.
I mean, I went by that wise voice like
this. I WENT BY THAT.
SO, you mean you mean to tell me you
wasn't that chili? You had an oldtime
with cheese. The girl you was with had a
three for me. Little light-skinned girl,
ragged split ends, mold on the right
side of her face. Drive a green Malibu
like shot up on the right hand side.
Work at the hospital on the third floor.
She's a phabotamist AND WENT TO HIGH
SCHOOL WITH ME. YOU WENT WITH
[screaming] HER AND YOU KNOW DUDES.
NOPE. Sure
[laughter]
wasn't.
But here it is. What I come to the thing
I had a um I was invited by this
Christian organization called Young
Life. They invited me to come perform
for all of their staff workers. All
their staff workers in Colorado Springs,
Colorado. Over 4,000 people there. uh
they gave me a number to come perform
that I thought was very healthy and so
I told them I will be there. I get to
Colorado Springs Colorado and I'm not
going to lie, I was a little nervous
because you know at this particular time
uh Young Life was you know really white
and and you know I speak with a lot of
slang, a lot of jargon, a lot of
colloquialism. So I didn't know how they
would receive it. So, I was a little
nervous and I remember being in the
restroom and a black dude walked in. He
was like, "Marcus D. Wy,
you funny." But I want to see how you
going to be in front of these white
folk. [laughter]
And I was like, "Hey, why you have to be
right next to me at the store, you know?
It's about 12 more stars. You ain't got
to be next door neighbor. Slide down."
But I needed to hear what he said
because what he said it freed me because
I got to thinking if I live in a quote
unquote white world surely they can come
in my world for 45 minutes. So I wasn't
nervous anymore. Right. And so uh ever
since then, you know, I've been talking
about my life when I'm on stage. I just
talk about my life, my family, my
children, my wife. My wife don't like it
all the time, but I have to tell her,
"Hey, this how we eat." [laughter]
Why you always talking about me? I say,
"Man, I talk about my life now. You a
big part of it. But if you want me to
get some new material, let me get in
these streets. [laughter]
Oh, I can get some new material. You
ain't going to like it, but I can get
some new material." So, anyway, I get on
stage. I do my thing
at the Young Life thing and and
[clears throat]
I sell my merchandise and I get back to
my um hotel. When I get back to my
hotel, uh about 30 minutes later, I hear
a knock on the door.
I was like, whoa. You know, cuz I didn't
order nothing. Um so I go look in the
peep hole. I see three white dudes out
there. I like, "Yeah, [laughter]
yeah. This this where Kobe got caught up
in Colorado." Uh,
I look back in the peeve hole, the black
dude from the restroom, he come stand
next to the three white guys. I said,
"Oh." So, I open the door. I said,
"What's up?" The little leader, he said,
"Hey, Marcus, man. We just come by to
tell you, great show tonight. The people
really loved you. Uh, but we were
wondering if we could pray for you.
>> [laughter]
[laughter]
>> I said, "For what?"
He said, "Well, you said some things
tonight about your wife."
[laughter] And we were just wondering if
we could pray for you. I said, "Oh,
yeah. No, no, no, no, man. Yeah, no. Me
and my wife good. Matter of fact, I just
got on the phone with her. You know,
them just jokes." He said, "Yeah, but
jokes,
they stem from a real place." [laughter]
I looked at the black dude. He was like,
"I tried to tell him."
[laughter]
And I don't know how to turn prayer
down. I'm I'm working on it cuz you
know, I don't want everybody praying for
me. But but I don't at that time I
didn't I ain't know how to turn it down.
You no I ain't know how to just tell
them you know get away. So, you know,
finally I acquies to the prayer and so
we holding hands. We're in the hallway
at the hotel. They like, "Bow your head,
close your eyes." I'm just like THIS
[laughter]
cuz I don't know what type of mood this
is.
They get through praying.
I go back in my room and I sat there and
I got to thinking, man,
I do these jokes all across the country
talking about my wife
at the black church.
[laughter]
And now one time
When I get off stage,
have anybody asked, could they pray for
me? [laughter]
But that ain't no shade to the black
church. It's because I know why they
need prayer, too.
That's when I realized we all are in
rehab.
If you are married, you are in rehab.
The definition of rehab, which is short
for rehabilitation, is the process the
body goes through to regain, maintain,
and improve after surgery. In my case,
rehab means it's the process your
marriage goes through to regain,
maintain, and improve after the wedding.
I told you on the last special, it's
major surgery.
See, most people get married think the
when is the finish line.
We've only just begun.
First thing I look at is is regain. Do
you know when you get married, you will
take some L's?
>> It's it's inevitable. You're going to
take some L's in marriage. People lose
respect for each other. People lose
appreciation.
>> Huh? People lose attraction.
Okay? And the big one, people lose
trust. But when you lose these things,
this ain't the time for you to be like,
"I'm gone." You got to regain it back.
Why not regain it with somebody you know
to try to go gain it with a complete
stranger?
>> Yeah. Regain. Here's a big one. The
trust thing is big, y'all. One New
Year's Eve, one New Year's Eve, I was in
Birmingham, Alabama, getting ready to
perform, you know, watch night service
and uh one of my partners, he drive
trucks. He he he a truck driver. And he
calls me out the blue. He say, "Hey,
Mark, [sighs] bro, I need your help." I
was like, "Man, calm down. What's going
on?" He say, "Man,
my wife, man, she man, we man, she
didn't I didn't got caught.
I said, "Man, calm down, bro." I said,
"Calm down, bro. You are you driving
right now?" He said, "Yeah." I said,
"What happened?" He said, "Man, we
talking about remodeling the house. We
was moving one of the bedrooms, making
at the office, making the office a
bedroom. So, my wife going to try to be
proactive and do some stuff before I get
home, and she took the computer, plugged
it up, and all these text messages came
from 5 years ago."
I said, "Oh my god." I said, "What she
say?" She just told me, "We'll talk
about it when I get home." I said, "Oh,
well, cool. You in good shape." He He
said, "Why you say that?" I said, "Cuz
you got what most men never have. Time."
Yeah, cuz most women they catch you in
the middle of the night. Just pull THAT
COVER. WHO IS FELICIA?
And you
can't get it together. Yeah. You got
time, cuz
I said, "How far are you from home?" He
said, "Okay, calm down, bro. calm down.
I was like, "Now, who is this?" Cuz I I
ain't know nothing about, you know, this
little affair he was having. I ain't
know nothing about who he So, he told me
a little story. I said, "Well, okay, let
me help you." Now, I know some of you
cuz I feel in my spirit. You're saying,
"Why did he call me?" That's that I can
read your mind. I'mma vaunting you.
You're saying, "Why did he call me?" I
tell you why he called me. He called me
because when you don't go to church and
don't know the Lord, the first person
you call is somebody that do.
Yeah. Why you think them gangsters have
their funeral at your church? They ain't
never been there.
Why they didn't have their funeral at
the club Bone Shakers? No. They want
somebody that KNOW THE LAW. SO ANYWAY,
HE CALLS ME, RIGHT? I said, "Bro, okay,
let me help you." I said, "Listen,
what's on the text messages?"
He said, "Man, I don't remember." I
said, "No, no, no. This ain't the time.
this ain't the time for you about I
don't remember. No, no, no. You got two
hours and I don't have that much time
cuz I'm about to get on stage. I said,
"What's on the text message?" He said,
"Man, Mark, that was over 5 years ago,
bro. I don't know." I said, "Okay, let
me ask you some questions." I said, "Um,
[sighs]
did you send any money? Is that on a
text message?" [laughter]
He said, "Oh, no, no, no. I I ain't
sending no money." I said, "Okay." I
said, "Okay." Was you on there talking
down about your wife? Like saying bad
things about your wife on a text
message? He said, "No, no, no. I want
doing that." I said, "What about
pictures? Did you see any nakeds?"
[laughter]
He was like, "No, no, I don't think none
of that on there." I said, "Here's the
big one.
Did you tell her you love her?
>> He said, "No." I said, "Oh, you good."
He said, "What?" I said, "You good?" I
said, "Listen, man. Won't you just go
home and confess? You got to take a L.
It's obvious you've been talking to
somebody. Just go home and tell the
truth. Whatever happened, whatever
reason why you do it, just tell the
truth, bro. You going to take a L. Just
be honest, bro. Don't be tripping. Just
go tell." He like, "Man, I don't know if
I" I said, "Brother,
go tell the truth. Trust me." I get a
call, [laughter]
January 1st.
Marcus, you a genius.
[laughter]
He said, "Bro, I did exactly what you
told me to do. I did exactly what you
said. I didn't deviate from the script
or nothing. We talked about it. We
cried. We made love, bro. Thank you.
Next time we go out, margaritas on me. I
mean, [laughter]
I said, "Cool." Holla. Hung up the
phone.
I get a call January 2nd.
[laughter]
She found some more text messages.
I said, "What you mean she found some
more text messages?" He talking about,
"I don't know. She was on the computer."
I said, "WHY YOU DIDN'T THROW THE
COMPUTER AWAY?
YOU OLD ENOUGH TO KNOW ABOUT WATERGATE.
Delete everything. THROW IT OUT THE
SECOND FLOOR, SECOND STORY BEDROOM. GET
RID OF IT. He going to say, "You didn't
tell me to do that." I said, "I DIDN'T
TELL I DIDN'T TELL YOU TO CHEAT.
YOU DID THAT ON YOUR OWN." [laughter]
I said, "Man, what did she find?" He
said, "Well,
it was a couple of pictures."
He says, "Also on that was a me and her
was talking about getting our kids
together on little play date."
>> I said, "What else?" [laughter]
He said, "And one time on there, I did
say
>> love you."
>> I say, "So you just lie to everybody.
I done turned to his wife. What you
ain't going to be doing is lying to me.
Yeah. Yeah. I don't like no liar. Right.
So, I told him, I said, "Well, look, uh,
I I'm out of it now. Um, you should have
told me this up front cuz then we would
had another play, but now good luck."
And so, I
GET A car
January 3rd, [laughter]
Mark.
Man, I ain't never seen her like this.
She being real mean. Mean to me. Mean to
the kids. Like the kids was in on the
play date. [laughter]
Man, I don't know what to do. He say,
"Can you come over here [laughter] and
talk to her?" I said, "Hey, cuz she
don't want to talk to nobody, you know,
right now. [laughter]
She mad at all of us." He said, "No,
Mark, she really respect you, bro.
Please do this for me, man. I need you.
I said, "Well, man, ask her if I can
come over there." He asked her. She
said, "Okay." I come over there.
[snorts]
I go in the living room. She in the
living room. He bring his little goofy
self in there. I said I said, "Hey, man.
Get out of here, cuz you about to mess
up everything I'm about to say. Every
time she I say something, SHE GOING TO
LOOK AT YOU and get mad." No. No. Get
out. So, I just went in there. I went in
there and I said, "Listen, however
you're feeling right now, you're well
within your right. whatever your
decision you want to do, you well within
your right. All right? You uh what he's
done is permissible for you now to get a
divorce.
>> But just cuz something is permissible
don't mean you should do it. And I just
told her I said I'm not here advocating
for him. I promise you I'm not cuz I
ain't know nothing about it. You know,
uh whether y'all together or not, he's
still gonna be my partner. But um I'm
not here trying to tell you he a good
dude cuz he's not.
I say cuz he's not. But what I don't
want you to do is make
an emotional decision. Times like these,
people like it's the end of times when
it's just one of them times. So just
take some time, think about it. Woo woo
woo. She said, "Marcus, thank you so
much for coming over here cuz I haven't
told my mama. I haven't told my friends.
I haven't told my sisters cuz I don't
want to embarrass him."
When she said that, I said, "Oh, he got
a good one."
I called Goofy back in the room.
[laughter]
We grabbed hands. I prayed for him.
I left.
I get a call. [laughter]
January 5th.
He talking about, "Mark, I can't take
this no more. I'm getting ready to
leave. I can't take it no more, man.
good. And then she'll just switch up on
me. I can't take this no more. I said,
"Hey, bro.
You are in the wrong." [laughter]
He was going to tell me, "Man, that's
old." I said, "No, it's it's new to her.
It's old to you." He thought he said
something mature. I just want to move
on. I said, "The guilty always want to
move on."
I told him, "But if you want your family
to remain together, then you need to do
whatever it take
as long as it take." Yeah. And if that
mean you driving your truck and she
facetime YOU, SHOW ME THAT TRUCK YOU
IN THAT HOTEL. SHOW ME THAT ROOM.
You got to DO WHAT YOU GOT TO DO.
YOU GOT TO DO WHAT YOU GOT TO DO TO
regain
trust.
People ask me, Mark, how am I
maintaining? So, me and Erica, my wife,
we've been married now 28 years. We've
married 28 years. Yeah. [cheering]
[applause] Yeah. Yeah. That's a long
time uh to be with the, you know, the
same one. And people always ask how we
maintain. So, I share
Me and my wife, we use what I call the
three C's to maintain. We use church,
we use the community, and we use the
calendar.
Church, community, the calendar. I got
to go to church. Church is the place
where I go. And when I hear about the
love of God, how he love
unconditionally, it put me in my place.
It let me know I ain't going to say
goofy stuff like I've outgrown her.
Huh? I hope people say, "Ah, [snorts] I
grown." As if that person can't grow.
You grew,
let them grow, you know, or help them
grow.
>> So, church, I I got to go to church,
right? Church. And then church also have
ministries in place that try to help
you. We don't even go to the marriage
ministry events. At my church, we go to
the single ministry events because they
the ones with the best events. Even when
they even when they advertise their
events, do you know they find the most
attractive singles to come up on the
platform to share with everybody what
they doing? It'd be the most attractive
female walking up there like a model.
She just walk on the platform. She got
dumps like a truck truck.
Thighs like what what
she up there lip gloss popping, hair
done, nails done, everything done.
And even the dude, the single dude, he
attractive. He got muscles, a V-neck
sweater with the with a V all the way to
his navl. He got a half a gallon of
Carmex on his lips. He up there with
shades on smiling and pointing at
everybody. [laughter]
Who don't want to go to that event?
[applause]
Oh man, but the married, they got the
oldest couple [laughter]
to come up here to tell everybody. Now,
I ain't got a problem with the couple
being old, but the old couple should not
be coming up here sharing with everybody
because they walk up there like this
here.
[laughter]
[laughter] Me and my wife be like,
"Yeah, we ain't going to that one.
We ain't going.
Singles have good events.
Skate parties,
pool parties,
sleepovers.
[laughter]
The singles at my church went to Vegas.
When they got back, we asked, "How was
it?" They talking about what happens in
Vegas.
>> What happens sin?
Marriage ministry.
Most of them they have this thing called
date your mate.
The fact that they got to tell you
[laughter]
to date your mate is an indication
that this ain't going to be good.
[laughter]
Date your mate. Me, I don't even think
date your mate is a is the right thing
they should say for a marriage ministry
because me and my wife don't date. See,
dating is when you gathering and
developing data about the person. I know
her.
Okay? And tonight, I don't want to talk.
I'm trying to see how we can make it
through this date or this night out and
get back to the crib and do something
nasty. That's the only thing. That's the
only thing we trying to do. Married
people don't date. We go out. We want as
little talking as possible because if
you call it date night, then what ends
up happening? Date night turns into
update night. And now you're talking and
you finding out stuff you should have
been knew about. Well, you know he got
suspended. WHAT YOU MEAN HE GOT
SUSPENDED? WHY AIN'T NOBODY TOLD ME
THAT? WELL, IF YOU BE HOME MORE, YOU
WOULD HAVE KNOWN AND NOW YOU done messed
up your little action tonight.
when we go out, we we don't want to
talk. Yeah, get on your phone. I'm cool.
I'm telling her, "Hey, bring another
margarita." "Yeah, keep it stay on your
phone."
So that's why I told my pastor, "If you
trying to keep me and my lady together,
we don't need another marriage prayer
breakfast. We don't need another
marriage seminar, another marriage
conference, another marriage retreat. If
you trying to keep me and my wife
together, get us a room at that
Marriott. [laughter]
Put some soft music, rose petals and
stuff in the bedroom. Give us some music
so me and my wife can do a little dance,
make a little love,
get down tonight.
I don't need no conference. [laughter]
The marriage community is how we
maintain
the marriage community. You got to get
them in a community with like minds.
People who are at least trying to keep
you together.
That's at least their first option is to
try to keep you together. They say stuff
like, "Don't blame Mr. Charlie.
[laughter]
Mr. Charlie is just a man and he
doing the best he can. They trying to
keep you
together. And I know a lot of married
people. You have single friends and they
some great friends. They some smart
friends. You take their advice about
this and about that. But what you cannot
take their advice about
>> marriage
>> is marriage.
>> Because they are going to talk to you
with a single mind. I'm not even mad at
them. That's just their mindset. It's a
single mindset. So everything you say,
it don't compute to them. One of the
main problems we having right now is um
social media. And I'm not here to poo
poo social media. I'm just here to share
with you. Be careful because on social
media, see, everybody can talk to you
>> and they not even in your community.
They not even on the same page on what
you talking about. Y'all don't even have
like minds, but they have an opinion.
They have a comment. Man, my team posted
something where I was well, I thought I
was giving my wife props. I was on an
interview on this podcast called Dear
Future Wifey. On this particular podcast
on Dear Future Wifey, the host, he has
started this podcast because he's trying
to get tips. He's trying to get um you
know just some good points and and some
things from people who are married or
have been married because he want to
make his next marriage a great marriage.
So that's what he built his podcast on.
Well, I'm on there talking about support
my wife supporting. I'm in there sharing
with him how man I need my wife. I need
her. I need her. I can get another girl.
You see me,
[cheering]
[applause]
but I can't get another her.
>> I need her. I was telling him how, man,
she run everything.
>> I can barely function, right? I was
like, "Bro, now don't get me wrong. I'm
intelligent enough to find out stuff,
but why? It's good. It's good to be in a
relationship where you need the other
person." And I'm just sharing that with
him. I'm like, "When she go out of town,
I got to FaceTime her." Hey, how do I
get Hulu on this,
[laughter]
man? How do I get this stuff? I have to
put the put the thing on on the remote
and SEE THE BUTTON OVER THERE. ALL THIS
TYPE OF STUFF. WELL, UNDER THE comments
was a bunch of single people, mainly
ladies, and no shade because single
people, they're talking and speaking
from a single mind.
>> I know that's your home girl, right? I
know she helped you uh through school
and helped you uh with your child and
helped you with this and he helped you
with that and you really value their
opinion. But if they single they still
have a single mind
bottom line. So under the thing one of
the ladies said
he seemed like a burden.
[laughter]
SHE CALLED ME A BURDEN.
I PAY ALL THE BILLS. [laughter]
I'M A BURDEN. RIGHT. THE OTHER lady
other lady, she came on there and the
lady going to say, "I want to be wanted,
not needed."
Cuz I said, "I need my wife." She said,
"I want to be want. I don't want no man
to need me. I want a man to want me."
And I had to say [sighs]
because before we got married, I wanted
her.
But then we got married
and I need her.
Wanted her.
Need her.
I want candy.
[laughter]
I need vegetables.
>> [applause]
[cheering]
>> So when you want to be wanted, stay
single.
Everybody want a single.
Other girl said on there, she going to
this a bit much. I can do bad all by
myself.
This is one of the stupidest things I've
ever heard in my life. We make stuff try
to make it sound good. I could do BAD BY
MYSELF. NOBODY in the world I know want
to do bad by theirel. When I see a
homeless person, he got or she got A
HOMELESS COMPANION.
NOBODY WANT TO DO BAD by themsel. YOU
SEE SOMEBODY STRUNG OUT ON DRUGS, THEY
GOT SOMEBODY STRUNG OUT ON DRUGS WITH
THEM. NOBODY WANT TO DO BAD. It's a
idiom that says misery.
>> DON'T NOBODY WANT TO DO BAD.
DO YOU KNOW the probability of doing
good is higher when you're with
somebody?
>> Yeah. And then the last one. Oh, the
last one. That's the one that took the
cake. He said ghee thought what he said
was a flex.
But really it was not because I'm
telling you right now, when does she get
a break?
That would get a break. And I be wanting
to go on there and talk so bad, but
[laughter]
got a single mind. It a it ain't going
to hit right. And so I'm like, a break?
First of all, marriage don't come with
breaks.
It don't. Ain't no breaks in marriage.
[clears throat]
I'm sorry to tell you, if it ain't the
marriage,
it's the kids. If it ain't the kids,
it's your friends. If it ain't your
friends, it's your family. If it ain't
your family, it's a job. Marriage don't
come with breaks. I've been paying
mortgages since 2005,
on time, never late.
And I'm waiting
for the mortgage company to call me and
say, "Marcus, because you've been so
good,
we want to give you a break this month."
Ain't no breaks with marriage.
Then we use the calendar, dog. You got
to use this calendar. you trying to
maintain, you got to use the calendar.
The calendar, it helps you. It's some
type of holiday. It's some type of
birthday, anniversary, some type of
celebration. You got to use it. Some of
you saying, "Hey, man." You know what
I'm saying? I don't celebrate that
stuff. Uh we don't celebrate it either.
We celebrate us.
>> Here it is. From January 1 to the first
weekend in February, which is the Super
Bowl. I know we not getting a divorce.
[laughter]
Because my wife throws a Super Bowl
party every year.
Every year. I don't care what didn't
happen in that time, she going to have
that party cuz she like to stunt on
them. Come here. Hey, this our house.
[cheering]
[applause]
Oh, you like that food? Okay, girl. That
cater one of my best friends. I'll get
that number to you. You know that WHAT
YOU WANT TO do
and people keep talking about but they
don't celebrate. We we don't celebrate
that we don't celebrate. Me and my wife
don't celebrate Cinco de Mayo. I can't
tell you what it's about. But I know we
about to get these margaritas.
Yeah. We better get these TWO FOR ONE
SINGLE DAY MAYO. SHE HATE WHEN IT'S ON A
Saturday cuz you got to sing at church
Sunday. Like I'll be over there.
Won't he do it?
>> [applause]
[laughter]
>> I always TALK ABOUT WHAT YOU DON'T
CELEBRATE. You don't celebrate Labor
Day, but you do. When Labor Day come
person who say they don't celebrate
holidays, go to their boss and say, "You
know what? I don't celebrate this. I
want to come to work on Labor Day."
You don't do it. You don't do it. You
got to use the calendar. And then when
you maintain, let me show you something.
It's like it's like um I noticed people
have what you call a destination wedding
but don't have no destination for their
marriage.
How is it that you got a destination
wedding
but no destination for marriage? See,
y'all work together on that wedding. Oh,
you work together. Did you Did you get
the boys? Do the boys got their tuxedos?
Do they got their shoes? All this type
of stuff. You had to work together
because if you're not working together,
you're working apart,
right? But you was very patient with the
wedding.
They tell you, "We can't get that venue.
Y'all can't get married here until 3
years from now.
I'll wait." [laughter]
You patient with the wedding. No
patience with the marriage.
when things go wrong for the wedding. Oh
man, we ordered the dresses. We wanted
our left shoulders out. They came in,
the right shoulder was out.
You had mercy on the seamstress.
Gave them grace, but no grace in the
marriage. No mercy in the marriage. Not
one time when things went wrong at that
wedding, did you say, "I'm going to
divorce that wedding."
[laughter]
You still We having that.
Yeah. So if you're not working together,
work it apart. Then improve.
This a tough one. Improve.
Improve. Got to regain, maintain,
improve.
One of my friends, his mom and dad, 75
years old, been married 50 years.
The husband come home one day,
looked his wife in the eyes and said, "I
want a divorce."
When she asked why and the kids, "Daddy,
why?" He say, "Because I'm not happy."
Can I please demonstrate to you tonight
what happiness should look like at 75?
[applause and cheering]
[cheering]
How happy DO YOU WANT TO BE?
WHEN I FOUND THIS OUT, THIS is when I
realized happy is your responsibility.
>> People love to say stuff like, "Man,
marriage is not what I thought it would
be. You're not what you thought you
would be." [laughter] When I read your
high school yearbook, you said you was
going to be doing this, living there,
MARRIED TO JANET JACKSON, ALL THIS TYPE
OF STUFF.
Ain't none of that manifested yet. So
why is you putting all of what you're
not
>> on marriage?
>> Happiness is your responsibility. And
happy and marriage don't even go
together.
[laughter] Watch this. This about to
bless you if you let it. Ah,
[applause]
happiness and marriage is two different
things. We think it go together because
for years women have been walking
wherever they at, grocery store,
walking, you know, working out at work
and a man come up to you, hey, hey, hey,
hey, hey. And woman, I'm married.
And you thought that stopped him. He'll
go happy.
Are you happily married? as if that
means something. It don't. Happy and
marriage, it don't go together. People
think it's like peanut butter and jelly.
And I've learned peanut butter and jelly
don't go together.
>> When I was a kid, my mama, we going to
the through the grocery store. We on the
peanut butter and jelly aisle. She sees
that they have concocted this thing with
the peanut butter and the jelly in the
same jar. She trying to save some money,
so she bought this. This was the worst
concoction
ever. [applause]
The reason is because I'm a peanut
butter guy. I like peanut butter. I just
need a little jelly. A little
I just need a little jelly to enhance
my peanut butter. And that's what
marriage do. When you are happy,
marriage enhance
your happiness. It can't even deduct
When you truly happy, you just be
disappointed in your spouse. Look at
you.
I'm so disappointed with y'all. I don't
know what TO DO. BUT YOU HAPPY THOUGH.
YOU STILL GOOD. They just
[laughter]
happy and marriage don't go together.
Are you happily married? It's like
asking me, am I happily black?
[laughter]
sometimes.
But I'd have been pulled over in the
middle of the night. I'D BE LIKE, "OH, I
WISH I was white right now."
[applause and cheering]
Yeah. But in order to get happy, you got
to improve
>> yourself.
That's right,
>> man. I got to give I I got to take a
little moment right here. I got to give
my wife props because when we were in
college, when we were in college, um my
wife came to me one day. I guess she was
very frustrated this day. We wasn't
married at the time. um boyfriend,
girlfriend. But she was like, "Um,
can you be with a girl that don't have a
degree?" I was like, "What test you just
failed?" No.
[laughter]
She was like, "Can you be with a girl
don't have a degree?" I was like,
"Yeah." I was like, "I ain't no thing. I
mean, my mom ain't got one. My grandma
don't have one. You know, I don't care
nothing about that." I said, "But you
going to have to work." Um
because at that time in my life at early
20s a girl that did not work was
unattractive to me. I'm just talking
that's to me. And so and she was like oh
I'm going to keep a job. I was like
okay. And I told her I said listen now
all my friends got degrees
and I don't want you to you know be
tripping like y'all throwing your
degrees in my no throwing them. We
earned them.
And she was like no I mean I I got that.
I said, "And hey, and then when you're
on these jobs and you going to get
skipped over
>> because you ain't going to have no
degree. I just want to let you know this
is what can happen, you know, not
having, you know, that paperwork." And
she was like, "Yeah, I got it. Cool."
Boom. So, we going we going through
life, man. We married. And then in the
pandemic,
wife come to me and say, "Hey,
I'm going back to school." I was like,
"In the pandemic?
you know I'm not getting booked right
now, don't you? She's like, "Yeah, I'm
I'm going back. I'm going back to I'm
going back to school." And man, that
girl went back to school and all the
stuff when we was dating that she wanted
to do, she went did she went got her
degree. She went pledged little Delta.
>> Hey, I I don't need the I don't need the
gang sign. I don't need the gang sign. I
don't I don't need all that right now. I
don't need that. But I'm just saying all
the things that she wanted to do back
then, she went back and she did it. And
when she got it, guess what? I regained
all type of admiration,
respect,
attraction cuz I like cuz she coaching
too. She she teach and she be coaching.
She come home, she got the heels in the
bag, she got the running shoes on,
lanyard around her neck. And I'll be
seeing out there, I'll be like, "She can
get it.
>> [laughter]
>> Yeah, I got a whole new attraction boy.
Now, [laughter] at the end of the day,
at the end of the day, what I learned is
people, they do not let the marriage
mature.
I said, they don't let the marriage
mature. People don't I mean, we live in
time now, everything like this here. If
it ain't the way you want it, ah, I'm
gone. And you got to let the marriage
mature.
I did this conference, Rainbow Coalition
Conference, Jesse Jackson. Yeah, he's
still alive.
Yeah. Yeah. I ain't lying. I was honored
when they called me, right? They called
me to do um they had a conference,
Rainbow Coalition conference, and they
had me do my comedy. And so I did my
comedy, right? And when I did I got off
stage, it was an it was an older
gentleman. Um he was uh sitting at my
table and this is a old civil rights guy
like he was in his 90s. He marched with
everybody and
you know real smooth sit there you know
old men sit on with the legs crossed and
he's sitting there and when I sat down
he said uh young man you were uh you
were phenomenal up there tonight. Um he
said um now did I hear you correctly?
Did you say that you were married?
>> I said uh yes sir. He said, "And how
many years?" I said, "28." He said, 'Oh,
you're a newlywed. Congratulations.
[laughter]
[laughter] I said, "What?"
He said, "You're a newlywed. Congrat."
Like, he was very condescending. You
You're a newlywed. Congratulations. I
done gotten mad at the man. I said, "You
married?" He said, "I am." I said, "How
long you been married?" He said, "71
years.
I said, "Oh, I am a newlywed."
[applause]
And I needed to hear this. I needed to
hear this because
I got partners at the barber shop.
They've been married six years, right?
And they ready to throw in the towel.
Can't take it no more.
I'm at the end of my rope.
Oh, I made a bad decision to do this.
And now I could tell him, "Dog,
your marriage is six.
Your marriage is in elementary.
[laughter]
Your marriage can't even get in a rated
R movie yet.
>> [laughter]
>> You got to let the marriage
mature.
>> Let me show you what I mean. You got to
let the marriage mature. Don't be so
quick.
Don't be so quick to just, you know,
throw something away that could possibly
be great.
Let it mature.
What I mean by that is y'all, I
I came from a home where they where they
cooked food.
[laughter]
This is the home that I grew up in.
They cooked food.
Then I got married. [laughter]
And I went to a home
>> where they fix food.
>> Cooking
>> and fixing
>> two different things.
You fix tuna fish.
You fix hamburger helper.
You fix riceeroni, nachos, hamburgers,
sandwiches. A lot of men in here get so
excited. Oh, my baby cooking tacos
tonight. No, your baby fixing tacos
tonight. [laughter]
Cooking is when you stuff something.
Cooking is when you smother something.
Cooking is when you sauté something.
Cooking is when you preheat the oven on
350 for 2 weeks.
When me and my wife got our first home,
we were in there building it up. We was
with the builder and my wife saw a
kitchen that cost $28,000.
She told the builder, "That's the
kitchen I want." She walked off. I told
the builder, "Come here.
Come here. We do not need a kitchen.
Give us a concession stand.
Cuz right now we on corn dogs, Frito
pies, grilled cheese. Why we need a
$28,000 kitchen buck?
[laughter]
I grew up in a home
where they cleaned up.
They cleaned up in the home I grew up
in.
>> I got married
[laughter]
and I went to a home where they
straightened up.
>> Cleaning up.
and straightening up.
Two different things.
All straightening up requires you to do
is get everything out of sight.
That's We got COMPANY COMING OVER. GET
IT UP. You can put it under the bed, in
the closet, in the garage, store it in
THE BACKYARD. JUST GET IT OUT OF HERE.
[laughter]
And then for breeze everything
[clears throat]
cleaning up, you smell it before you see
it.
Put the key in the door.
>> Soon as you open it, you already smell
bleach.
>> Pine saw pine o pine faboso.
[applause]
Cleaning up requires a wet rag,
not a wet nap. Put that back in your
purse. A wet rag. See, you got everybody
up at night with all this. [groaning]
You think it's your allergies? No. No.
No. If you GET A WET RAG, GET ALL THAT
DUST OFF THAT CEILING FAN.
>> [cheering]
>> But don't miss it
because if you leave early
and don't let the marriage mature,
if I would have aborted that thing, I
never would have seen the girl
who fix
become
a cooker.
If I don't let the marriage mature and I
leave early,
I never would have seen the girl who
straighten up.
Well, we really got a housekeeper come
every every Friday. My wife was like, "I
AIN'T DOING BOTH OF THEM. I'M NOT YOUR
MAMA. YOU SHOULD HAVE MARRIED YOUR
MAMA." HEY, I'M MARCUS D. WALLY. It's my
time.
[cheering]
[music]
>> [music]
>> Hey,
[music]
hey, hey. [music]
>> [music]
>> Hey,
[music]
hey,